<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Diacatholicon aureum: or a generall power of gold purging all offensiue humours in mans bodie: good in generall for all diseases, where there needeth any purgation: as also for any sicknesse yearely incident, or which is feared to approach by the increase of any euill humor, distemperature of diet, or otherwise how so euer growing towards any disease, to preuent the same, and keepe the bodie in health. It may lately be taken of all maner of people, of what age so euer, sucking children, old men and women, in the quantitie of two, three, or foure graines, according to the age, strength, and disease of the partie. Whosoeuer stand in neede of this powder, may haue it at the signe of the Hand and Pistall, neere vnto Iuic Bridge, for two shillings sixe pence the graine.</title>
            <author>Russel, Thomas, an empiric.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837451</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837451</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11188)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1005:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Diacatholicon aureum: or a generall power of gold purging all offensiue humours in mans bodie: good in generall for all diseases, where there needeth any purgation: as also for any sicknesse yearely incident, or which is feared to approach by the increase of any euill humor, distemperature of diet, or otherwise how so euer growing towards any disease, to preuent the same, and keepe the bodie in health. It may lately be taken of all maner of people, of what age so euer, sucking children, old men and women, in the quantitie of two, three, or foure graines, according to the age, strength, and disease of the partie. Whosoeuer stand in neede of this powder, may haue it at the signe of the Hand and Pistall, neere vnto Iuic Bridge, for two shillings sixe pence the graine.</title>
                  <author>Russel, Thomas, an empiric.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by S. Stafford] for Iohn Flasket,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Russel.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>British Library copy only copy.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gold --  Theraputic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIACATHOLICON AVREVM: <hi>Or</hi> A generall powder of Gold, purging all <hi>offenſiue humours in mans</hi> BODIE: Good in generall for all diſeaſes, where there needeth any Purgation: As alſo for any ſickneſſe yearely incident, or which is feared to approach by the increaſe of any euill humour, diſtemperature of diet, or otherwiſe how ſo euer growing towards any diſeaſe, to preuent the ſame, and keepe the bodie in health.</p>
            <p>It may ſafely be taken of all maner of people, of what age ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, ſucking Children, old men and women, in the quantitie of two, three, or foure Graines, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the age, ſtrength, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe of the partie.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer ſtand in neede of this powder, may haue it at the ſigne of the Hand and Piſtall, neere vnto Iuie Bridge, for two ſhillinge ſixe pence the Graine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hordea cui cordi demum ſerit hordea, ne tu</l>
               <l>Nunc aliunde pares auri primordia, in auro</l>
               <l>Semina ſunt auri: quamuis abſtruſa recedant</l>
               <l>Longius, &amp; nobis multo quaerenda labore.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Iohn Flasket. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhipfull Doctors and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Phiſicke of the Colledge in London, authorized by <hi>ancient Charter: and the reſt of the Doctors, profeſſors and</hi> Students of the ſame learned facultie, either reſident in the Vniuerſities of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford:</hi> Or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where diſperſiuely placed, and authorized in <hi>any cities or townes through this Realme of</hi> England: <hi>Encreaſe of knowledge, and proſperous ſucceſſe in your ſeuerall affaires and cures, to the glory of God, good of his people, and aduancement of your profeſſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very Art and facultie (Right worſhipfull Doctors, profeſſors and Students in the neceſſary and honourable facultie of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke) whoſe foundation is not layd on demonſtration, but onely on probable and phiſicall coniectures, is in it ſelfe ſo hidden and intricate, that euen about the principles, elements and grounds thereof, there are diuers and almoſt contrary opinions: from whence in euery ſuch facultie ſpring vp diuers heads of ſects, which in time infinitely multiplie, and as this propoſition we ſee by experience true in all generalities, ſo in this facultie of Phiſicke it is dayly verified. Hence in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens time (as he witneſſeth in his booke <hi>Deſectis</hi>) there were three ſorts of Phiſicians: the firſt which were called <hi>Emperici</hi> and <hi>Memores:</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Dogmatici</hi> and <hi>Rationales:</hi> the third, <hi>Methodici</hi> and <hi>Abbreuiatores:</hi> to theſe three, this age hath added a fourth, called <hi>Paracelſians,</hi> but they themſelues would be called the ancient Phiſicians, the true Philoſophers, the Chimiſts, and the Spageriſts, to ſet downe the groundes of either of their profeſſions, the opinions on either ſides: their arguments to maintaine thoſe opinions, would be to enter into a large fielde of diſcourſe, which at this time is not mine intent to doe, left I might ſay with the Poet, <hi>Ante diem clauſo componet veſper Olympo:</hi> this only hath here moued me to mention them, thus to ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:1772:3"/>
mine opinion of them in briefe, that whereas ſome doe attribute ſo much to diſtillations and preparations of Minerals, Animales, and Vegetables, that they firmely hold both the parts of Phiſicke as well <hi>Hygeinen</hi> as <hi>Thera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peyticen</hi> to bee completely perfourmed onely by them, and others ſo much wilfully bent or ignorantly ſeduced againſt the true intended perfection of Phiſicke, doe contrarily hold, that it is onely deſperate and dangerous Phiſicke which is attempted by minerals, prepared by the Spagiricall arte, and that it had bene farre better, that it had ſlept in ſilence and neuer bene knowen to the world. Betwixt theſe two extremes I thinke it beſt to hold a meane, ſo that I neither allow the extremitie of the one, nor imbrace the defects of the other: but mine opinion is, that both the ſorts of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinable preparation of ſimples, as well that which is done by the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries craft, as alſo by the Spagiricall art, I ſay, both of them haue their proper place and neceſſary vſes in Phiſick, <hi>(amicus Plato, amicus Ariſtoteles, ſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis amica veritas)</hi> ſo that I iudge this latter age of the world much bound to the careful ſearchers out of thoſe hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecrets of nature, which are ſo bound vp in minerals and vegetables, and outwardly do not appeare but by extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and magiſterie, and great folly it were vtterly to reiect them as many wilfully doe. Let them but attentiuely reade <hi>Hippocrates</hi> booke <hi>De arte,</hi> and ſee how he there deciphereth out a wiſe man, and a mad malicious foole, the wiſedome of the one conſiſting in the finding out in arts, thoſe things which are not yet found out, and in the bringing imperfect things to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect end, but the malicious fooliſhneſſe of the other being ſeene in rayling on thoſe things which are already found out, controlling, but not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting any thing amiſſe. The wordes of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> are theſe, <hi>Eorum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quae nondum inuenta ſunt inuenire, quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inueniſſe quam non inueniſſe prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiterit, ſimiliter<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imperfecta ad finem deducere id mihi videtur illius eſſe munus, qui intelligens exiflimari expetit: qui vero ea quae ab aliis ſunt inuenta inhoneſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum verborum artificio contaminare contendit, neque quicquam corrigit, ſed a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruis inuenta apud imperitos traducit, is ſane prudentiae exiſtimationem tueri velle non videtur, ſed potius naturam ſuam at ignorantiam malitioſe prodere.</hi> By which wordes it is manifeſt, that <hi>Hippocrates</hi> did not ſo ambitiouſly preſume vpon his owne knowledge and abſolute perfection in this facultie of Phiſicke: but that he did confeſſe, &amp; as it were intimate, that the time would be, when as it would be bettered by far, and brought to more perfection, which <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> himſelfe did propheſie of in his booke <hi>De priſca medicina,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging there, that only an entrance was found out to Phiſicke, but more excellenter things by farre in proceſſe of time ſhould bee: the words are theſe: <hi>In medicina principium &amp; via inuenta eſt, per quam praeclara multa longo temporis ſpatio ſunt inuenta, &amp; reliqua deinceps inuenientur ſi quis probe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus fuerit, vt ex inuentorum cognitione ad ipſorum inueſtigationem feratur.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1772:3"/>
Which <hi>Galen</hi> alſo affirmeth in the concluſion of his booke intitled, <hi>Quod op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus medicus idem ſit &amp; philoſophus,</hi> affirming there, that if we diligently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our ſelues to the ſtudie of Philoſophie, and ſeeke to bee true emulators of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> ſo doing we may become not onely like to him, but farre excelling, truely vnderſtanding thoſe things which are deliuered by him, &amp; finding out by our owne induſtrie, thoſe things which remain in the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Phiſicke, vnknowen by the wordes: therefore both of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> there were many things in Phiſicke which were vnknowen to them, and in their time not found out, <hi>Galen</hi> himſelfe witneſsing in the ninth booke <hi>De ſimplicium medicamentorum facultate,</hi> that he had neuer tried whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Quickſiluer, being applied outwardly or taken inwardly, would kill or no. So by both their iudgements thoſe were worthy of praiſe and not diſcredit, which by the true grounds of natural philoſophie, and by the help of thoſe things truely deliuered and ſet downe by thoſe two pillars of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, did by all labour indeuour to finde out more excellent things for the curing of diſeaſes. Yea, which is more, we are enforced (leſt open ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and reproch ſhould redound to the art) to ſeeke out newe remedies for ſome diſeaſes which were vnknowen both to <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> as the French Pox, the Meaſils, and the Engliſh ſweate, and others of the like kind, otherwiſe Phiſicke would hardly be deemed an arte.</p>
            <p>Theſe two graue and reuerend fathers of Phiſicke I haue therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged (though neceſsity and common good had bene a ſufficient ſhielde for this mine enterpriſe) that vnder the couerture of their wings, <hi>tanquam ſub Palladis aegide,</hi> I might be ſhadowed from reproch &amp; blame, and hauing two ſuch ſtrong Atlaſſes, I might the better beare the burden of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince which I haue vndertaken, namely, to publiſh to the world, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your Worſhips good conſiderations, triall and equall cenſures, an vniuerſall purging powder made of golde, ſiluer, and minerall water by arte and ſire to that perfection decocted, whoſe operation and vertues I haue briefly ſet downe in the ſmall Treatiſe following, referring the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular vſe of it to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of euery Phiſician, to ſpecificate it at his own diſcretion with any other purging ſimple, that it may worke the effect ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and bee more properly directed to any humor afflicting, or peculiar member afflicted: and although in the publiſhing of a true ſecret, I neither vſe dialecticall arguments to enforce, rhetoricall perſwaſions to allure, Lawyers il-loquence to vrge, Poets fictions to delight, Painters colours to deceiue, all which may make that ſeeme to bee which is not, and that which is, ſeeme not to be: yet this I humbly intreate, that as I nakedly delyuer an approoued trueth, ſo it may curteouſly be cenſured, as it ſhal be found by perfect triall: for Trueths auncient Hierogliphicke, is a virgine bare and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and hauing no deformitie, being from toppe to toe pure, vnſpotted and
<pb facs="tcp:1772:4"/>
beautifull, needeth no borrowed or counterfeit colours. This powder I preſent vnto your Worſhips, and make knowen vnto the world, for the loue and increaſe of the deſired perfection of Phiſicke, and the generall good of the diſeaſed, and withall for mine owne commoditie, being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto animated by the graunted authoritie of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other of our neotericke claſsicke Phiſicians, leſt ſuch a ſecret in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke ſhould bee buried in his owne aſhes, the publiſhing whereof, I hope, ſhal not giue any offence to the learned, but wil rather bee allowed and gladly accepted: which done, I reſt humbly at your Worſhips pleaſures and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, deuoting vnto you the fruits of all my hopes and ſtudies.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Ruſſel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:4"/>
            <head>G. N. Gentleman.</head>
            <l>LEt Antioch keepe their raging Scammonie,</l>
            <l>And ſend that cancred bane to Barbarie.</l>
            <l>Let deadly Colocinthis bitter gall,</l>
            <l>On great Armenia's craggie mountaines fall.</l>
            <l>Let Tithimal make Perſian widdowes weepe,</l>
            <l>And India ſtill their harmeful Turbith keepe:</l>
            <l>Since Englands happie Ile ſmall ſtand's in need,</l>
            <l>Of any ſuch farre-ſet outlandiſh weed.</l>
            <l>For here the Sunn's faire beames doe ſhine ſo bright,</l>
            <l>As leſſer Starres are like to loſe their light.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>G. P. Philoſophiae chimiſticae <hi>Studioſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>TIme lay's in duſt the Monarkes of each age,</l>
               <l>When al their pompe doth ceaſe, and princely grace.</l>
               <l>Time made ſtrong Milon weepe, and Helen rage,</l>
               <l>He for weake arm's, ſhee for her wrinckled face.</l>
               <l>Time caus'd Pyramides in Memphis plaine,</l>
               <l>Lowly to kiſſe their mother earth againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Hart, long'ſt-liu'd of euerie beaſt in field,</l>
               <l>The oke, the flint, the ſteele by ſturdie ſtrength,</l>
               <l>And each thing elſe vnder the Moone, doth yeeld</l>
               <l>To dint of death, and change of time at length.</l>
               <l>Onely this glorious ſhining Sunne on earth,</l>
               <l>At whoſe celeſtiall frame, and wondrous birth,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nature did equalize, fire, water, ayre,</l>
               <l>With pureſt yellow earth, moſt duely mixed:</l>
               <l>No time, nor meanes, can vtterly impaire,</l>
               <l>But ſtill remaineth vniforme, and fixed.</l>
               <l>Then ſince no time the ſubiect can deface,</l>
               <l>How then can any time thy name outrace?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:5"/>
            <head>G. K. in Artibus magiſter.</head>
            <l>EAch wit for wiſhed health makes beſt inuention:</l>
            <l>Some poſt a ſhip to fetch home Indian weed's.</l>
            <l>Some heape a maſſe of drugges, whoſe ſilly mixion</l>
            <l>May blindly hap to cure, yet oft the griefe it feed's.</l>
            <l>But all that loue to trie ſome certaine remedie,</l>
            <l>Applie and taſte this true, much labour'd miſterie,</l>
            <l>Extracting health from Gold, in whoſe center,</l>
            <l>Of all foure element's, ther's perfect temper.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>In Zoilum.</head>
            <l>TO praiſe the Authors worth, that craues his triall,</l>
            <l>Were of his owne intent a flat deniall.</l>
            <l>The Sophies of the world doe claime the Art,</l>
            <l>The matters influence rules euerie hart.</l>
            <l>Therefore to praiſe his skill or matter done,</l>
            <l>Were but to light a candle in the Sunne.</l>
            <l>And if ſome Momus be ſo mad to chide,</l>
            <l>He hath his due, to reſt vnſatisfide.</l>
            <l>So for aduantage, and for trials fame,</l>
            <l>I ceaſe, till he giue cauſe himſelfe to ſhame.</l>
            <l>And if by him in ſecret it be hiſt,</l>
            <l>Who but a Cow doth ſhun the open liſt?</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. W. Medicus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1772:5"/>
            <head>DIACATHOLICON AVREVM: <hi>Or</hi> A generall powder of Gold, purging all <hi>offenſiue humours in mans</hi> BODIE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. I. Whereof the powder is made, and of the Philoſophicall preparation of it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoeuer the Almightie diſpoſer of vniuerſall nature, hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſiuely infuſed in the generalitie of naturall things, either celeſtiall or terreſtriall, the ſame is collectiuely found in one particular of the ſame kind; as for example, what vertue, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, or influence is diſperſiuely placed in euerie Starre, Orbe, or bodie celeſtiall vnder the firſt mouer, the ſame is found vnited in one Sunne. What animall faculties are diſperſed in all ſeuerall liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, are gathered together in one man. What hidden vertue ſoeuer, is diſperſiuely infuſed in minerals, is collectiuely vnited in one metall, which is Gold, and this is the principall materiall whereof this powder conſiſteth. But for abbreuiation of time and labor, ſince it is hard to make a perfect calcination of Gold by it ſelfe, I haue therfore, following the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Auicen,</hi> and wonne with his reaſons, added a due proportion of the other perfect metall, that thereby their agent might make a better ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliation of them, which agent in the compoſition, is the third ingredient, being a ſpiritualized metall in the forme of minerall water. Theſe thrée ingredients onely enter this powder and no more: which I terme by the name of <hi>Diacatholicon Aureum,</hi> becauſe that the chiefeſt thing, and moſt
<pb facs="tcp:1772:6"/>
in quantitie in the compoſition is Gold, being brought to that wondrous actiue qualitie by the true minerall fire, which is the agent and long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall decoction: neither doe I vſe either in my preparation or decoction, any thing but thoſe thrée ingredients; that this is true, I can make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to any man by demonſtratiue practiſe before his eyes, on which I wil engage goods, life, and credite, that there neuer came either common Quickſiluer prepared or vnprepared, Antimonie, Stibium, meane mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, vttriall, ſalts, powder, ſtrong water, imperfect mettall, or any other ſuch like thing whatſoeuer, but onely thoſe thrée ingredients before na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. How I came by this powder, what time I ſpent in the ſpeculatiue part of the Magiſterie, what labour and coſt in the experimentall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it, how often I miſſed in the practiſe before I could attaine to the perfection of it, if I ſhould here declare, would but wearie the reader, trouble the Printer, waſt much paper, ſeeme to ſharpe cenſurers, affected and ſelfe conceited diſcourſes, in mine owne cenſure néedleſſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in the end little to the purpoſe. Omitting therefore all ſuch vaine and néedleſſe diſcourſes, I will procéede to ſhew the vertues and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. Of the nature and qualitie of this Catholicon Aureum.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HIppocrates</hi> in the ſecond <hi>Apho.</hi> of his firſt booke, and the 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. and 9. <hi>Aphor.</hi> of the fourth booke, maketh mention of two ſortes of purging medicines, the one by vomit, the other by ſiege: Of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging medicines by vomit, <hi>Meſue</hi> in his firſt booke, <hi>De ſimplicibus medicamentis Purgantibus,</hi> the firſt Theorem, maketh a thréefold diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, taken from their facultie more or leſſe. The firſt he termeth vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which extreamely diſturbe nature, as white Hellebor, and Tithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, &amp;c. The ſecond meane, as <hi>Nux vomica and Nitrum.</hi> The third mild, as Onion ſéed and Radiſh. But of ſimple medicines which purge by ſiege, he maketh a fourefold difference. The firſt, are ſuch as purge by diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the humours, and being diſſolued by attraction of them from the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per parts, or eradication from the lower parts, not that the medicine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiued into the ſtomacke, doth penetrate the veines or the ſolid parts of the bodie to euacuate the humor, but by a certaine attractiue qualitie, doth draw his choyſe and familiar humor through the veines and paſſages of the bodie, into the ſtomacke and bowels, euen as we ſee Iet or Amber draw little ſtrawes, or the Loadſtone Iron, though they touch them not: of this kind, are Scammonie, Colocinthis and Turbith. The ſecond kind
<pb facs="tcp:1772:6"/>
of purging ſimples, are ſuch as doe not draw, but onely purge by driuing and preſſing out, drying and conſuming the putrid excrements, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward binding the bodie as Mirabolanes, and Tamaryndes. The third ſort purge by mollifying the humors within the ſtomacke and bowels, as Caſſia fiſtula and Manna. The fourth and laſt, by making them ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as the Muſcilage of Pſillium and Mallowes: theſe thrée latter kinds of purgers haue a weake facultie, and therefore ſcarce perſpicuous, euacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating onely thoſe humors within the ſtomacke and bowels, which there they méete withall, not paſſing the lyuer or working any thing by attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The firſt kind of purging medicines which worke by attraction, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> in his booke entitled, <hi>Quos purgare oportet,</hi> doth pronounce that they are all of a hot qualitie. <hi>Omnia medicamenta purgantia facultate ſunt cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> which in naturall Phyloſophie muſt néedes be graunted, for there are but two actiue qualities, heate &amp; cold, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> witneſſeth in his fourth booke of his <hi>Meteorologickes,</hi> the firſt Chapter.</p>
               <p>Now it is manifeſt, that it is the nature of heate alone to draw, for cold cannot doe it: therefore whatſoeuer purgeth by attraction, muſt néedes bée of a hot temperature. This being well knowne and conſidered, let vs ſee how all theſe kind of purgers worke, and the reaſon why, and then come to ſhew the nature and operation of this <hi>Catholicon Aureum. Galen</hi> in the fift booke of the facultie of ſimple medicines, affirmeth, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer purgeth, hath a facultie to worke on his peculiar and proper humour, ſome on one, ſome on two, and ſome on more; and that which is proper to any one humour, neuer worketh on another, vnleſſe the malignitie of the medicine, or the quantitie of the doſe do too much excéede, which <hi>Galen</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo witneſſeth in his booke, <hi>De purgantium Medicamentoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facultate. Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> alſo confirmeth it in his booke, <hi>De natura humana,</hi> ſaying there, That if a medicine be adminiſtred to bring forth fleame, it onely bringeth out fleame: if to purge choler, it onely purgeth choler: if to euacuate melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, it onely euacuateth that humour: to whome <hi>Meſue</hi> conſenteth in his firſt booke, <hi>De ſimp. medi. purg.</hi> the firſt Theorem, affirming more plainly, that if a medicine be giuen to purge melancholy, though choler and fleame abound much more in the bodie, yet it leaueth them, and purgeth melancholy, his own peculiar and deſtinate humor: whence, they haue this ſtrange facultie, the ſame Authors opinion is, that it proceedeth not from the temperature of the medicine (meaning the firſt qualities) nor from one contrarie working on another, nor from like drawing his like, nor as a light medicine vpward, a heauie downward, ſtirring the matter to be purged: but <hi>Quia talem coelitus eſt ſortitum facultatem:</hi> That the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie of euerie purging medicine, procéedeth from an heauenly qualitie and hidden influence.</p>
               <p>Now hauing ſhewed the nature and differences of purging ſimples, after
<pb facs="tcp:1772:7"/>
what ſort they worke, and by what meanes out of their Theoricke, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth after perfect inueſtigation both by cauſe and effect, to ſet downe the nature and operation of this <hi>Catholicon Aureum,</hi> or generall purging powder of Gold. Then, whereas I ſaid before in the beginning, that all purges worke either by vomit it or ſiege, this powder of Gold worketh both vp vomit and ſiege: yet let not this derogate any thing from the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of it, that it worketh by vomit: for although I muſt néedes confeſſe, that euerie action of any part made againſt the firſt ordinance of nature, is improſperous and vnfit, and ſo ſéeing nature did at firſt ordaine the <hi>Gula</hi> for attraction, and the <hi>Pilorum</hi> for expulſion: therefore by conſequent, all vomits made by contrarie motion to nature, are improſperous and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: although I ſay, this be ſimply true and cannot be denied, yet reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely &amp; by accident, vomits are not onely not hurtful, but verie commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and neceſſarie as well for the curing of diſeaſes, as for the regiment of health. For when there is aboundance of light Choler, thin water, and fleame ſwimming on the top of the ſtomacke, the expulſiue facultie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not driue them downward, by reaſon of their lightneſſe, neither is nature able to digeſt them, ſo they muſt of neceſſitie be euacuated by vomit, and ſo of two euils the leſſe muſt bee choſen, this way of purging being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and commended by <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and mightily confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the <hi>Academie</hi> of <hi>Salerne,</hi> preſcribing for the regiment of health to vomit once a month. To which of the foure differences of purging medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines to referre this powder, is a matter verie difficult, ſeeing it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet truely and Philoſophically determined by any Paracelſian, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mercurie or any minerall purge did worke <hi>Attrahendo humores,</hi> by drawing the humours together into the ſtomacke. But my aſſertion is, that this powder of Gold doth not worke <hi>Attrahendo,</hi> or <hi>Comprimendo,</hi> and <hi>Exprimendo,</hi> but <hi>Leniendo,</hi> and <hi>Lubricando,</hi> which I prooue thus.</p>
               <p>There is no cold medicine which doeth purge by Attraction; but the outward qualitie in the ſuperficies of this powder, from whence the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging facultie procéedeth (as is plainely ſhewed in the end of the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) is cold, therefore ꝑ conclude, that it cannot draw any humors into the ſtomacke. My propoſition was proued before by the naturall effectes of heate and cold, and by the authoritie of <hi>Galen</hi> before cited, in his booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled: <hi>Quos purgere oportete</hi> and in his fift booke, <hi>De ſimp. medi. facul.</hi> the ſixtéene Chapter. My aſſumption I proue thus: as is the effect, ſo is the cauſe: but the effect which Mercurie worketh is cold, and therefore Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie it ſelfe is cold: My propoſition in the Philoſophers maxime, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption is proued by inſtance in the diſeaſe called the Palſie, and relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Sinewes, which we ſee dayly happen to thoſe that deals much with Quickſiluer, as our Gilders with rich Gold, being cauſed by the
<pb facs="tcp:1772:7"/>
ſinne of the Quickſiluer. Now that the Palſie is a cold diſeaſe, <hi>Galen</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in his fourth booke <hi>De cauſis pulſuum.</hi> My ſecond inſtance is taken from another effect of Mercurie, which is this, When any hath taken a great quantitie, as much as will poyſon a bodie, during all the time of the working of it, the partie ſhall neuer thirſt, which if it were hot, it would inflame the bloud and vitall ſpirits, and cauſe intolerable thirſt, as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth after the taking of all hot poyſons, for the partie will thirſt euen to the death, which is proued by an example cited of <hi>Conciliator,</hi> in his booke <hi>De venenis,</hi> of an Apothecarie, who thirſting in the extreame heate of Summer, in the night time tooke a Pitchard of Quickſiluer in ſtead of ſome drinke or other, and dranke of it, forthwith it cooled his thirſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gealed the bloud, and deſtroyed the vitall ſpirits, and being found dead in his bed in the morning, his body by the aduice of a Phiſicion was cut vp, and there was found in his ſtomack one pound of Quickſiluer, the bloud in his heart being congealed: by which the ſame Authour concluded, that it was of a cold qualitie.</p>
               <p>To theſe inſtances may be added, that it is in the forme of water alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without taſte, not bitter, ſharpe, ſowre, ſalt, ſwéete, or hauing any ſtiplicitie or corroſiueneſſe. Beſides theſe probable inductions, the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of diuers of our moderne Authors may be added, who haue diligently both by ſpeculation and proofe inueſtigated the nature of it, whatſoeuer <hi>Paracelſus</hi> through vaine ſubtilties and trifling arguments, goeth about to perſwade the world that it is of a hot qualitie: then ſince the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall purging qualitie of this powder is cold, it manifeſtly proueth that it doth not purge by attraction. The ſecond reaſon which proueth that this powder doth not purge by attraction, is taken from a ſure demonſtration by certaine experience, which is this. The firſt time that it is adminiſtred vnto any bodie, it will worke his effect duely as it ought to doe, euacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the humours, but if it bee adminiſtred againe the next day, it will then verie little worke by ſiege or vomit, or nothing at all, by reaſon the firſt day it did euacuate all the humours within the ſtomacke and bowels, which it then met withall: now all other purges attractiue being taken againe the ſecond day, will worke afreſh, becauſe they ſtill drawe mo humours out of the veines and fleſhie parts of the bodie, and if there bee none to draw, they diſſolue and melt the fleſh it ſelfe, draw bloud out of the veines, &amp; ſpirits out of the arteries, and ſo by conſequent life it ſelfe: which vice would alſo bee incident to this powder of Gold, if it did worke any whit by attraction, which ſeeing it doth not, it cannot hold with the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall poſſibilitie of this powder, to produce any ſuch fatall euent: and as it worketh not <hi>Attrahendo,</hi> ſo neither doth it worke <hi>Comprimendo,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it leaueth the bodie after alwayes ſoluble, ſometimes a weeke, a
<pb facs="tcp:1772:8"/>
month, yea, a quarter of a yeere: by which may bee noted the excellencie and preheminence that this purge hath aboue all other purging medicines in the world: for this muſt needes be graunted, which <hi>Galen</hi> himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth in his booke entituled, <hi>Quos purgare oportet,</hi> That al purging me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines which worke by attraction, are verie offenſiue to the ſtomacke, and noyſome to all parts of the bodie, diuers ſymptomes and great incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences following them, by reaſon when there is ſuch a ſuddaine vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and vnnaturall pulling, and riuing the humours from bloud wherein life conſiſteth, nature can hardly endure, this ſeperation being before ſo firmely vnited together, without her great detriment and loſſe of many ſpirits, the inconueniences and vices whereof, I will ſhew at large in the ſixt Chapter.</p>
               <p>Now this purge of Gold, ſeeing it worketh not by attraction, cannot be ſcandalized with any of thoſe blots, neither can any ſuch ſymptomes follow it. But happily ſome may here obiect, that if it onely purge <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendo</hi> and <hi>Lubricando,</hi> and not <hi>Attrahendo;</hi> how can it remoue and purge ſtubborne and rebellious humors, out of the veines and ſolid remote parts of the bodie, and then not being able to remoue them, how can it be good almoſt for any diſeaſe: and to conclude, it were as good to take a gliſter, or eate a little Caſſia, Manna, or ſtued Pruines, as to take this golden purge. To this I anſwere, that though it purge not the humours within the veines and fleſhie parts by attraction: yet it doth either helpe nature to digeſt them, or expell them by ſweate and Vrine, which is a direct courſe according to natures owne procéedings: ſo you ſee that it doth worke by vomit, ſiege, ſweate, and vrine, according as nature is burdened and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerladed: for if the ſtomacke bee oppreſſed with light choler, water, and flegme, it purgeth them by vomit: if the inteſtines and lower parts bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercharged with choler, water, or flegme, it worketh by ſiege: if either ſtomacke or bowels be ouerladen with melancholy, it euacuateth alwaies that humour by ſiege: if the bloud and the ſolid parts of the bodie bee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with any of thoſe humours, it diſſolueth them and openeth their paſſage, and purgeth them by ſweate and inſenſible expiration. If the Emulgent veines or reynes of the backe be burdened with choler, flegme, or melancholy, or haue any obſtructions, it openeth the paſſages, diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the humours, and bringeth them out by Vrine; for it purgeth all the vicious and offenſiue humours alike, not hauing any humour deſtinate to it, but as the body is moſt ouercharged, on that it worketh firſt. In the anſwering this obiection, a greater may ariſe among the learned, and that is this: Whereas I ſay that this powder of Gold dooth purge by ſweate and Vrine, how can that agrée with naturall Philoſophie and experience, that a cold qualitie (which I affirmed before this powder had) can open,
<pb facs="tcp:1772:8"/>
diſſolue, ſweate, and expell by Vrine. To this I anſwere, that though the outward ſuperficiall qualitie of this powder of Gold bee cold, from the Mercurialitie, yet inwardly there is a ſubtill acrious heate, from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reitie, which is ſtirred vp and animated by the naturall heats of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and brought in <hi>Energian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nature being alwayes wiſe in her working, making ſeperation of the cold qualitie in the ſuperficies of the medicine, to worke by vomit and ſiege: and ſelecting the ſubtill inward medicinable vertue, drawing it into the veynes to helpe her ſelfe to worke away all that offendeth her, ſhée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alwayes prone to her emendation and perfection. And thus I haue ſhewed in generall the nature and working of this powder of Gold; but fearing leſt I haue excéeded thoſe ſtraite limits I alotted my ſelfe, I am enforced to omit many things that were expedient to bee ſpoken of this matter: onely touching theſe things, as briefe as I could, which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie; but if there be any that reſts not contented with that which here is ſaid, I will by conference fully ſatiſfie him at any occaſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. How and in what quantitie this powder is to bee taken.</head>
               <p>COmmonly for a ſucking child two graines will ſuffice, for youth thrée graines, for middle age and moſt ſort of people foure graines, for ſtrong folkes and ſtubborne diſeaſes fiue graines. It may bee taken in a ſpoonefull of drinke, <hi>Aqua-vitae,</hi> or ſpirit of Wine, in the pappe of an Apple, or a Quince, in the pulpe of Rayſens or Pruines, in a little broth, in conſerue of Roſes or Barberies, or in any ſuch like thing: Or if it pleaſe the Phiſicion in any ſirupe, powder, electuarie or potion, proper to that diſeaſe, or eſpeciall humour which he doth intend to purge, which I leaue to the learned diſcretion of euerie Phiſicion, who may well determine of euery particular patient, which in generalitie it is impoſſible for me to doe: but particularly I can direct any that ſhall require it for what intent ſo euer, either in Pill, Potion, Lezenge or Electuarie, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as ſhall beſt fit the diſeaſe, and the Patients content.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:1772:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. Of the preparation of the bodie, and time when this powder is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to the intent that any man may vſe it, that hath not the Phiſician al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at hand.</head>
               <p>SInce there are diuers that inhabit in the Countrie farre from any Phiſician, which cannot eaſily reſort to one when they ſtand in need: and diuers of the poorer ſort of people, that are not of ſufficient abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to pay the Phiſician for his counſell, and the Apothecarie for his drugs, therfore I thought it conuenient to ſignifie thus much vnto them, or to any other that are determined to take it, how they ſhall take it, and how to prepare their bodie and make it fit, for what purpoſe ſo euer they would haue it. If there be any therefore which to the intent to kéepe their bodies in health, or to preuent any vſuall ſickneſſe incident vnto them, or hauing alreadie any Ague, weakneſſe of the ſtomacke, or moleſted with ſuperfluitie of humours, or any diſeaſe mentioned in the Chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by the opinion of the Phiſician; I ſay, if any of theſe be determined to take of this powder, let them firſt conſider, whether they doe intend to ſweate much or little, at the time of the working of it: if much, let them kéepe them warme in their bed; if little, let them ſit vp by a fire in their Chamber: Then let them conſider whether they would haue it worke more by vomit then ſiege, or more by ſiege then by vomit. If they would haue it worke more by vomit; firſt, let them eate a great meales meate ouernight: but if they would haue it worke more by ſiege, let them eate ouernight verie little or faſt altogether. Secondly, if they would it worke more by vomit then by ſiege, let them a little after they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, drink fiue or ſixe ſpoonefuls of warme water, and ſaliet Oyle, or warme water alone. But if they would haue it work by more ſiege, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſently after they haue taken it, drink fiue or ſixe ſpoonefuls of cold water: but whether they would haue it worke by vomit or ſiege, let them ouernight take be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſupper, if they ſup at all, or in ſtead of their ſupper, as many of theſe Pruines as they pleaſe. Take water, or Rheniſh wine, or both together, and diſſolue pure Engliſh Honie in it, or Sugar, as much as will make Mead, or Sirup of it, and in this Sirup, let the beſt damaſke Pruines be ſtued.</p>
               <p>Take ouernight of theſe Pruines and the Sirup, as much as you will; or take Sirup of the infuſion of Roſes, or Sirup of Vineger, or any ſuch gentle ſoluble thing to prepare the bodie before: but after they haue taken
<pb facs="tcp:1772:9"/>
the powder, during all the time of the working of it, drinke the wherof Poſſet drinke, made with clarified Mace, &amp; Ale. And at dinner, eate ſome breth made with light meate at ſupper, and afterward vſe your ordinarie diet, but ſparingly at firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. For what diſeaſes this powder is good.</head>
               <p>SEeing that this powder doth purge all offenſiue humours to mans nature, as well ſimple as mixed: therefore I conclude, that this <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicon</hi> is good for al diſeaſes, when as there néedeth any Purgation of any humour, either vpward, downeward, by ſweate, or Vrine; for the cauſe remooued, the effect muſt néedes ceaſe, and in this kind it may haue the preheminence aboue all other purging medicines, which euer Art or inuention till this day found out: and although it may iuſtly challenge this preheminence both by art and nature, namely by the matter whereof and the meanes whereby it is made, yet are other ſimples and confections ne're the worſe, nor leſſe to be regarded, for euen they in their due place and time may bee mixed with this, to make a more peculiar purging medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, more ſpecificate to any member affected or humor exceeding. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer it farre excelleth them all in theſe properties, namely in the ſmalnes of the quantitie, the aptneſſe of the receite, the not offenſiueneſſe in taſte; ſoone, ſafe and pleaſantly working his effect, and in the wholeſomneſſe of it to mans body, euen by the teſtimonie of <hi>Meſue</hi> himſelfe, affirming thoſe to be the wholeſomeſt purges which are ſwéete or without taſte: For this being adminiſtred in the quantitie of two, thrée, foure, or fiue graines at the moſt, may as well be taken as a péece of bread, or ſpoonefull of drinke, and hauing no taſte, neuer offendeth the Patient, as ſhall be ſhewed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; for here with breuitie, I intend to ſet downe the chiefe diſeaſes for which this powder is ſpecially good, and leaue the reſt to the good cenſtoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Phiſician.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Headache proceedeth from choler, flegme, or melancholy, or mixt humour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Headache from an euill ſtomacke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Megrim.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Vertigo or Turnabout.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Dead ſleepe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Apoplexy.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1772:10"/>7 <hi>Frenſie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Loſſe of memorie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Noli me tangere, Cancer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Eriſipelas.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>Carbuncle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>Elephantiaſis.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 <hi>Puſtles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14 <hi>Scabs and Itch.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>15 <hi>Leproſie, or any tumors againſt nature.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16 <hi>Cough.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>17 <hi>Aſthma, or difficultie of breathing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>18 <hi>Inflamation of the Lungs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>19 <hi>Spitting of matter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>20 <hi>Ptiſicke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>21 <hi>Pleureſie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>22 <hi>Spitting of bloud.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>23 <hi>Swounding.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>24 <hi>Weakneſſe of the ſtomacke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>25 <hi>Vomiting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>26 <hi>Great thirſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>27 <hi>Loſſe of appetite.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>28 <hi>Doglike appetite.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>29 <hi>Surfeting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>30 <hi>Sighing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>31 <hi>The night Mare.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>32 <hi>The Cholicke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>33 <hi>Iliaca paſsio.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>34 <hi>Windineſſe in the bodie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>35 <hi>All ſortes of Wormes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>36 <hi>Fluxes, Lienteria, Diſſenteria, and Diarrhaea, becauſe in the beginning it is good to purge away the vicious humour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>37 <hi>The Emmorrhoids or Piles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>38 <hi>Obſtructions and diſtemperature of the Liuer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>39 <hi>Iaundiſe, yellow and blacke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>40 <hi>The Greene ſickneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>41 <hi>The Dropſie, Anaſarcha, Vpoſarcha, and Timpanites.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>42 <hi>The obſtructions of the Splene.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>43 <hi>Flatus melancholicus hypoc.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>44 <hi>Vlceration of the Reynes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>45 <hi>The Stone or grauell in the Reynes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>46 <hi>Strangurie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1772:10"/>47 <hi>Difficultie of piſsing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>48 <hi>Piſsing of bloud.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>49 <hi>For bringing down womens Flowers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>50 <hi>Sterilitie or barrenneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>51 <hi>The quotidian Ague.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>52 <hi>The Tertian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>53 <hi>The burning Feuer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>54 <hi>The Quartane.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>55 <hi>The Peſtilence.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>In all theſe diſeaſes it is good to take of this powder, yet imagine not that this of it ſelfe will cure them perfectly, yet many of them it will, as moſt ſort of Headaches, &amp; weaknes of the ſtomacke, all ſorts of wormes, the thrée Fluxes with an other ſimple after the body is purged, the Stone in the reynes, womens termes, &amp; all maner of Agues (the Feuer Hecticke, and Maraſmus excepted) whether the humours bee enflamed within the veynes or without, in al maner of people, ſucking children and other, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly at once taking, but for the Quartan it will aſke longer time. Alſo I preſume it wil cure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peſtilence if it be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any time, &amp; not paſt al help.</p>
               <p>Finally, for the French Pox<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or any ſimptome therof beginning, it is the moſt ſingular medicine that euer was found out, for without hot-houſes, lothſome diet drinkes, bathing in Cornelius Tub, any other Purgations, annoyntments, fumes, or Suffumigations with Quickſiluer, making moſt lothſome Excoriations and painefull Exulcerations, eating the teeth out of the head, and diſſoluing the Sinewes, and other ſimptomes, this onely of it ſelfe, if it be taken before the deſperate ſymptomes doe appeare, will cure them, and doubtleſſe excelleth all other that art or nature can this day afford.</p>
               <p>In like maner it may be probably coniectured, by the authoritie of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Authors, and reaſoning from the materials whereof it is made, that it may cure the Gout, if it be not alreadie grown to a deſperate period. Now that I haue ſhewed for what diſeaſes this powder is good, ſome may expect that I ſhould ſet downe the particular experiences that I haue made of it, to wit, the Cures which it hath performed, with the names of the parties, the time when, &amp; the place of their abode, to the intent it might the better perſwade the hard beleeuing world, of the good effects of it, &amp; giue greater credit to my words. But for theſe cauſes I haue wittingly &amp; willingly omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: firſt, in regard that many of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties are not willing to haue their names come in print, nor the diſeaſes knowne of which they haue béene cured. Secondly, the rehearſal of theſe cures performed by my ſelfe and my friends which haue adminiſtred it, would aſke a longer diſcourſe then all my treatiſe beſides. Laſtly, I might haply be condemned of too much arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy &amp; vainglory, ſéeming to incline for the moſt part to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperical ſect. To auoid therefore imagined arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, tediouſneſſe in diſcourſes, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure to my friends, I haue purpoſely neglected that which might well here haue beene ſpoken of this large ſubiect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:1772:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6. What ſymptomes and accidences happen after the taking of this powder.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Think it not impertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this purpoſe, firſt to ſhew what ſymptomes and inconueniences follow and happen to the bodie after vſuall purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that thereby the difference betwéene them &amp; this powder of gold may be plainely perceiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> in his booke entituled, <hi>Quos oportet purgare,</hi> giueth a generall and true propoſition of all purging medicines: <hi>Omnia purgantia medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta ventriculum vitiant, praecipue<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> os ipſius, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Meſue</hi> largely confirmeth in his firſt booke <hi>De ſimp. medic. purga.</hi> the firſt theorem, whereto all other Phiſicions with one conſent agrée, and by experience we ſee it daily verified: and they doe not onely hurt the ſtomacke in particular, but are alſo grieuous to nature itſelfe, offending the principall parts of the bodie, ſo that the diligent ſearchers out of their faculties and operations haue noted theſe ſymptomes which vſually follow the taking of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The firſt is, Agues, becauſe they doe inflame the humours. The ſecond, Cepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalgia, by reaſon of their vapours fuming vp into the head. The third, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigo, cauſed by the circumaction of vapours rayſed vp into the braine with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his ventricles and arteries. The 4. imbecility of ſight, by reaſon of too much drineſſe of the parts of the eyes, which follow ſuperfluous euacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of the humour within the nerue optick, which thoſe purges diſſolue and cannot euacuate. The 5. weakeneſſe of the ſtomacke, cauſed diuers wayes by the diſtemperature which the medicine bred. The 6. immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thirſt, cauſed by the ſaltneſſe, ſharpneſſe, heate and bitterneſſe of the medicine. The 7. ſighing, cauſed either of immoderate heat and acrimony of the medicine gnawing the ſtomacke, or by his drineſſe drawing it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The 8. payne of the ſtomacke, cauſed of the vnequall diſtempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or exulceration which the purge made. The 9. excoriation of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels, through the corroſiue and fretting qualitie of the medicine. The 10. inflamation of the reynes, procéeding from the heate of the medicine. 11. The ſtone of the reynes, by reaſon of abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſlimy matter brought to that place, and by heat baked into a ſtone. 12. Voyding of bloud, prouoked by the vlceration of the bowels. 13. Tenaſmus, or a vayne deſire to goe to ſtoole, by reaſon the ſpincter or muſcle of the fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is vlcerated through the acrimony of the medicine or humour voyded. 14. The Emmorrhoids or Plies cauſed by ſuch medicines as open the veynes. 15. Imbecility or
<pb facs="tcp:1772:11"/>
weakeneſſe of the whole bodie, by reaſon of the generall diſturbance of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, cauſed by the violence of the medicine. 16. Convulſion, cauſed of much matter ſtirred vp and drawne together, but not euacuated, which after hauing recourſe to the ſinewes and muſcles, cauſeth convulſion. 17. Coſtiueneſſe, the body being left hot and drie after the purge, and then ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the excrements, which doth happen in ſundrie purgations, &amp; moſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients complaine of it. All which diſeaſes do happen to them that take pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations for three eſpeciall cauſes, being thrée maine vices incident to moſt of vſuall medicines that purge. The firſt, when they doe moue, diſſolue, and draw together offenſiue humors, and nature not able to euacuate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſecond, when humours are euacuate illegitmately and with moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Patient, which happeneth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are miniſtred for thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours which they ought not. The third, when they doe too much euacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, working too violently, making excoriation of the ſtomack and bowels, and drawing the bloud out of the veynes. For the correction of theſe ſymptoms, the learned Phiſicions in all ages, hauing eſpeciall care of their Patients health, laboured by all means poſſible to find out Antidotes and correctors to withſtand their inconueniences, and breake their malice: and in regard each purging medicine had ſome manifeſt vice or other, they did not onely inuent generall correctors to auoyd ſuch capitall vices, but alſo particular for euery ſuch medicine. Hence Aloes had Maſtick, Bdellium, and Tragagant, to keepe it from opening of the veynes &amp; drawing bloud out of them, and cauſing the Emmorrhoids. Mirabolanes were prepared with oyle of ſweete Almonds, and adminiſtred with iuice of Fumitary, Wormwood, Agarick, and Spikenard, and Diureticks, to hinder them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſing obſtructions. Scammony was corrected with iuice of Quinces and vineger, to breake his malice, and giuen with Aromaticks and comforters of the principall parts, to ouercome his enmitie to the whole bodie. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith was corrected with Ginger, to auoyd windineſſe: and ſo in like maner euery one had his particular correcter, directer, and helper to worke duly, &amp; qualifie their vices. This knowne and well conſidered, it reſteth to ſhew whether there be any ſuch vice in this <hi>Catholicon Aureum</hi> or no; &amp; herein is the difference ſéene betwéene this and all other purges, that whereas all of them néed correctors to breake their malice, Aromatickes to take away their lothſomneſſe and help their working, admixture of contraries to ſtay their violent and immoderate operation, and Cordials to comfort &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the principall parts: So that if the ill effects they worke, be weighed in an equall ballance with their good, the good will ſcarce counterpoyſe it. This powder onely hath this grace, that it neuer offendeth any of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts, neuer draweth bloud out of the veynes, neuer worketh too vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently, euacuating more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is burdenſome to nature, neuer inflameth the
<pb facs="tcp:1772:12"/>
bloud, or any part of the body, neuer maketh exulceration of the ſtomack &amp; bowels, neuer violently draweth humours, but after a direct courſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth nature to digeſt them or expell them by ſweat, vrine, and expiration, neuer néedeth any corrector, nor hath any ſuch inconuenience: therefore by conſequent, neuer raiſeth any ſuch ſymptoms which vſually follow the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the other purges, but contrarywiſe I affirme that it ſtrengtheneth the heart, the liuer, the braine, and the whole body, purifieth the bloud, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiueth the ſpirits, making them fit and apt to doe all their functions natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. That this is true, I giue the learned thus much to conſider. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials whereof this powder conſiſteth in generall are two, for in it are two corporeall ſubſtances mixed and vnited together, not as <hi>Elementa in compoſito mixta inſeperabilia,</hi> but as ſalt diſſolued and mixed with water, or ſugar in wine <hi>per minima</hi> as farre as that mixion and vnicion may be, yet with more fixation and very hard (yet poſſible) ſeperation. One of the ſubſtances is Metalline fixed, the other Mercuriall fixed agent &amp; pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Of theſe two vnited together is this powder made; from theſe two in one, procéed two ſeuerall qualities, the one purging by ſiege <hi>Leniendo</hi> and <hi>Lubricando;</hi> by vomit <hi>Os ſtomachi aperiendo,</hi> and <hi>Naturam fortiter mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendo.</hi> The other comforting from the Aureity, and helping naturall heat to diſſolue open, and expell whatſoeuer is offenſiue either within the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, or without, by ſweat and expiration: and as neither Mercury it ſelfe without his incorruptible patient can ſafely purge or work any good effect, ſo neither Gold without his Mercuriall agent the true minerall fire, can be ſo ſubtiliate as to comfort nature &amp; expell offenſiue humours, but both Philoſophically circulate together make this perfect purge. From theſe reaſons it may be gathered, why it both purgeth and comforteth, from the one qualitie leauing the body long after ſoluble, from the other qualitie ſtrengthening the vitall ſpirits and animall faculties, reſtoring alſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heat and radicall moyſture to the temperature thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7. The concluſion.</head>
               <p>CVrteous Reader, I haue thus bréefely and truely ſhewed the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials whereof this powder conſiſteth, the preparation of it, the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and operation, the differences betwéene this and all other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and in what diſeaſes it is good to take it; yet imagine not that it will cure them of it ſelfe alone, but onely ſeruing for a preparation to their cures, whereſoeuer there néedeth any purging in ſtead of all other,
<pb facs="tcp:1772:12"/>
yet many of thoſe diſeaſes as I noted before, it will of it ſelfe cure, with diuers others which time and experience ſhall make manifeſt, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious Reader may eaſily gather fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inſtance of thoſe, and that with more effectuall, ſafe, pleaſant, and ſpeedice working, then any other at this day known and inuented: and if any hereafter require farther ſatiſfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the naturall poſſibilitie hereof, either by authority, reaſon, or experience, I ſhall bee ready at any occaſion to doe it, eyther by word or writing; in the meane time commending theſe firſt fruites of my labours to his indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and equall cenſure, <hi>Et hic me Plato ſiſtere iubet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
